<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc PUBLIC "-//IETF//DTD RFC 2629//EN"
"http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2617 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2617.xml">
<!ENTITY UMA PUBLIC "" "http://kantarainitiative.org/confluence/display/uma/Home">
<!ENTITY UMAreqs PUBLIC "" "http://kantarainitiative.org/confluence/display/uma/UMA+Requirements">
<!ENTITY RFC3552 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4627 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4627.xml">
]>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-maler-oauth-umatrust-02" ipr="trust200902">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

  <?rfc toc='yes' ?>

  <?rfc tocdepth='4' ?>

  <?rfc symrefs='yes' ?>

  <?rfc sortrefs='yes' ?>

  <?rfc compact='yes' ?>

  <?rfc subcompact='no' ?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="UMA Binding Obligations">Binding Obligations on
    User-Managed Access (UMA) Participants</title>

    <author fullname="Eve Maler" initials="E" role="editor" surname="Maler">
      <organization>XMLgrrl.com</organization>

      <address>
        <email>eve@xmlgrrl.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Thomas Hardjono" initials="T" surname="Hardjono">
      <organization>MIT</organization>

      <address>
        <email>hardjono@mit.edu</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="27" month="January" year="2014"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>User-Managed Access (UMA) is a profile of OAuth 2.0. UMA defines how
      resource owners can control protected-resource access by clients
      operated by arbitrary requesting parties, where the resources reside on
      any number of resource servers, and where a centralized authorization
      server governs access based on resource owner policy. This document
      provides a contractual framework that defines the minimum obligations of
      parties that operate and use UMA-conforming software programs and
      services. The goal of this framework is to support end-to-end legal
      enforceability of the terms and conditions of access sharing
      relationships between authorizing and requesting sides that use UMA. The
      audience for this document includes technologists, legal professionals,
      and operators of UMA-conforming services.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>User-Managed Access (UMA) <xref target="UMAcore"/> is a profile of
      OAuth 2.0. UMA defines how resource owners can control
      protected-resource access by clients operated by arbitrary requesting
      parties, where the resources reside on any number of resource servers,
      and where a centralized authorization server governs access based on
      resource owner policy. This document provides a contractual framework
      that defines the minimum obligations of parties that operate and use
      UMA-conforming software programs and services. The goal of this
      framework is to support end-to-end legal enforceability of the terms and
      conditions of access sharing relationships between authorizing and
      requesting sides that use UMA. The audience for this document includes
      technologists, legal professionals, and operators of UMA-conforming
      services.</t>

      <t>Capitalized terms and abbreviations used in this document are defined
      in <xref target="terminology-clauses"/> because they form a normative
      part of the framework defined in <xref target="clauses"/>. Readers are
      strongly encouraged to review these definitions before reading the rest
      of the introduction.</t>

      <section title="Sample Use Cases for Sharing Access to Resources">
        <t>UMA makes possible a loosely coupled end-to-end access sharing
        relationship between an Authorizing Party and a Requesting Party, with
        its primary goals being to constrain access according to the
        Authorizing Party's access policies and to encourage the Requesting
        Party to adhere to any obligations it consented to in the
        authorization process by raising the consequences for doing otherwise.
        Following are sample use cases that explore the potential differences
        in these obligations beyond the basic level represented in the
        contractual framework.<list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Person-to-self sharing">Here, Alice is both the
            Authorizing Party and the Requesting Party. This use case
            describes most types of today's OAuth-mediated access, for
            example, when Alice introduces the Klout service to her Twitter
            account. She uses both services herself, and wants them to
            communicate together on her behalf. With UMA, Alice can
            potentially manage the entire set of such access connections from
            a single place rather than from Twitter and other online "home
            bases" separately. In this circumstance, it's unlikely Alice will
            want to impose stringent contract terms on herself.</t>

            <t hangText="Person-to-person sharing">Here, Alice is an
            Authorizing Party and Bob is a Requesting Party. Today, many Web
            2.0 sites offer some level of selective sharing between people,
            but methods, strengths, and interfaces are inconsistent between
            sites and people are unable to reuse policies across sites. Alice
            can share Flickr photos with Bob by adding him to her Flickr
            friends list or family list or by mailing him a special link to a
            photo album, or Alice can add Bob as a friend on Facebook. With
            UMA, Alice can craft authorization policies that let Bob "qualify
            in" to get access to her photo album and even to other resources
            she manages at other sites, without her having to be present
            during this process.</t>

            <t hangText="Mediated person-to-organization sharing">Here, Alice
            is an Authorizing Party, the DentalCare company is a Requesting
            Party, and the company's office assistant Carl is a Requesting
            Party Agent. Alice wants to give her dentist's office, DentalCare,
            temporary access to her calendar to make it easier to schedule a
            series of root canal appointments. Carl might be the actual person
            acting on behalf of the dental practice who actually asks for and
            views Alice's calendar. With UMA, Alice can require Carl to prove
            he is acting on behalf of DentalCare -- for example, demonstrating
            control of an email address in the dentalcare.com domain -- before
            seeing her calendar.</t>

            <t hangText="Autonomous person-to-organization sharing">Here,
            Alice is an Authorizing Party and the Valley Vehicles car
            dealership is a Requesting Party. Alice has crafted a "personal
            request for proposals" because she's in the market for a new car,
            and she's willing to let car dealerships in her region of the
            country see her request and make offers to her. With UMA, Valley
            Vehicles and other dealerships might use Web crawler services to
            go out and collect requests for proposals, without human helpers,
            and these services might have to prove in automated fashion that
            they legitimately represent the right kind of business. Alice can
            also ensure each dealership agrees to her terms before seeing her
            request for proposals.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="How to Use the Contractual Framework">
        <t>The contractual framework in <xref target="clauses"/> is the
        normative portion of this document. It is intended to apply to all
        Subjects that take part in software interactions using services that
        are declared to be UMA-conforming. It defines the minimum set of
        obligations that these Subjects accept. The Subjects can adopt
        additional obligations, and can further refine or constrain the
        obligations listed here, but cannot make these minimum obligations
        less strict.</t>

        <t>Each clause takes the following form:</t>

        <t>"[<spanx>Clause ID</spanx>]. When [<spanx>protocol interaction takes place</spanx>],
        the [<spanx>obligated Subject</spanx>] gains an obligation to the
        [<spanx>expecting Subject</spanx>] to [<spanx>behave towards it in a particular way</spanx>]."</t>

        <t>The clause ID has the following internal structure:</t>

        <t>"[<spanx>obligated</spanx>]-[<spanx>expecting</spanx>]-[<spanx>keyword</spanx>]"</t>

        <t>It uses abbreviations for the obligated and expecting Subjects as
        follows: RqP for Requesting Party, RSO for Resource Server Operator,
        ASO for Authorization Server Operator, and AzP for Authorizing Party.
        Clauses are generally followed by non-normative explanatory comments,
        which are labeled with "Comments:", and occasionally open issues,
        which are labeled with "Issues:". The latter are meant to be resolved
        and removed before final publication.</t>

        <t>Specific obligations come as a result of precise protocol
        interactions, so that at a moment in time, any one Subject may not yet
        have taken on all of the obligations defined in the contractual
        framework as belonging to that Subject. By analogy, if Alice were to
        visit a website that imposes terms of service on the site's users, but
        it requires users to consent actively by clicking on an "I Agree"
        button, Alice would take on terms-of-service obligations only after
        she clicks on the button.</t>

        <t>Following are the key UMA interactions that result in obligations,
        with specific cross-references into the <xref target="UMAcore"/>
        specification. A non-normative visual correlation of interactions to
        binding obligations can be found at <xref target="UMAFAQ-swim"/>.
        (Lowercase versions of names are references to constructs in the
        technical specification versus this document.)<list style="symbols">
            <t>An authorization server issues a protection API token (PAT) to
            a resource server: Section 1.3.1.</t>

            <t>An authorization server issues an authorization API token (AAT)
            to a client: Section 1.3.1.</t>

            <t>An authorization server issues a requesting party token (RPT)
            to a client: Section 3.4.1.</t>

            <t>An authorization server responds positively to a client's
            authorization request: Section 3.4.2.</t>

            <t>A resource server determines the status of an RPT: Section
            3.3.</t>

            <t>A resource server registers a client-requested permission:
            Section 3.2.</t>

            <t>A requesting party supplies claims to an authorization server:
            Section 3.5.</t>

            <t>A resource server responds to a client's request for access:
            Sections 3.1.1 and 3.1.2.</t>

            <t>A client successfully receives access: Section 3.1.2.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Obligations Not in the Scope of the Contractual Framework">
        <t>Of the Subject types defined and discussed in this document, some
        -- Requesting Party Agents and Client Operators -- have no
        UMA-dictated obligations, though they might have obligations as part
        of contractual agreements with other UMA-related Subjects, for
        example, pairwise contracts or membership in trust frameworks.
        Additionally, pairs or groups of Subjects that do have obligations
        imposed by the contractual framework might have additional obligations
        among themselves beyond those in the framework. Following are some
        typical examples:<list style="symbols">
            <t>When a Resource Owner registers for an account at a Resource
            Server, the Authorizing Party might gain an obligation to the
            Resource Server Operator to adhere to the Resource Server
            Operator's terms of service.</t>

            <t>When a Client registers with an Authorization Server for OAuth
            client credentials (for example, through an explicit approval
            process or through a passive "API-wrap" process), the Client
            Operator might gain an obligation to the Authorization Server
            Operator (apart from any particular Requesting Party's usage of
            that Client) to adhere to the Authorization Server Operator's
            terms of service for API clients.</t>

            <t>When a Subject becomes a Requesting Party Agent for a
            Requesting Party (for example, through an employment agreement),
            the Requesting Party Agent might gain an obligation to adhere to
            any agent agreements in place in the Subject's UMA-related
            interactions performed on behalf of the Requesting Party.</t>

            <t>When a Requesting Party contracts with a Client Operator to
            engage in UMA-related interactions on the Requesting Party's
            behalf, the Client Operator might gain an obligation to adhere to
            the terms of that contract. For example, a car dealership may
            contract out to use a cloud service that crawls the Web looking
            for personal RFPs that meet the dealership's criteria, and want to
            impose confidentiality requirements.</t>

            <t>When a Client accesses a protected resource at a Resource
            Server, the Resource Server Operator might gain an obligation to
            the Client Operator to be trustworthy as a source of the expected
            data. For example, in a scenario where the Requesting Party is
            also the Authorizing Party and is trying to fill in an online loan
            application through an online financial service (the Client),
            where the Resource Server Operator provides credit risk data about
            the Authorizing User, the Client Operator will want to
            authenticate the Resource Server service in some fashion.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="clauses" title="Binding Obligations on UMA Participants">
      <t>This section constitutes a normative framework that defines the
      minimum obligations gained by parties that operate and use software
      programs and services that the operators declare to be UMA-conforming.
      The framework consists of clauses, where each subsection with content is
      a clause.</t>

      <section anchor="terminology-clauses" title="Terminology">
        <section title="Terms">
          <t/>

          <t>This framework uses the following terms. Where terms are used
          without capitalization and are not otherwise defined in the <xref
          target="UMAcore"/>, they are used in their normal sense.<list
              hangIndent="6" style="hanging">
              <t anchor="Individual" hangText="Individual"><vspace/>A natural
              person (that is, a human being) with the capacity to take on
              contractual duties and obligations as a participant in an UMA
              interaction.</t>

              <t anchor="Non-PersonEntity"
              hangText="Non-Person Entity (NPE)"><vspace/>A legal person (such
              as a corporation) with the capacity to take on contractual
              duties and obligations as a participant in an UMA
              interaction.</t>

              <t anchor="Subject" hangText="Subject"><vspace/>An Individual or
              NPE. Subjects play various roles in achieving and seeking
              user-managed access, and the same Subject might serve in
              multiple contractual roles.</t>

              <t anchor="Conformance" hangText="Conformance"><vspace/>Claimed
              adherence of a running software program or service to the
              requirements of one or more of the roles "authorization server",
              "resource server", or "client", as defined in <xref
              target="UMAcore"/>. Software components play various roles in
              participating in the technical interactions necessary to achieve
              and seek user-managed access, and the same software component
              might serve in multiple technical roles.</t>

              <t anchor="AuthorizingParty"
              hangText="Authorizing Party"><vspace/>A Subject that fills the
              "resource owner" role as defined in <xref target="UMAcore"/>,
              using and configuring software services that variously fill the
              "authorization server" and "resource server" roles. This Subject
              is the "user" in "User-Managed Access"; UMA's first priority is
              to enable Individuals to serve in the Authorizing Party role,
              though NPEs can serve in this role as well.</t>

              <t anchor="AuthorizationManager"
              hangText="Authorization Server"><vspace/>A software service that
              fills the "authorization server" role as defined in <xref
              target="UMAcore"/>.</t>

              <t anchor="AMOperator"
              hangText="Authorization Server Operator"><vspace/>A Subject
              responsible for running and operating an Authorization
              Server.</t>

              <t anchor="Host" hangText="Resource Server"><vspace/>A software
              service that fills the "resource server" role as defined in
              <xref target="UMAcore"/>.</t>

              <t anchor="HostOperator"
              hangText="Resource Server Operator"><vspace/>A Subject
              responsible for running and operating a Resource Server.</t>

              <t anchor="Requester" hangText="Client"><vspace/>A software
              application or service that fills the "client" role as defined
              in <xref target="UMAcore"/>.</t>

              <t anchor="RequesterOperator"
              hangText="Client Operator"><vspace/>A Subject responsible for
              running and operating a Client.</t>

              <t anchor="RequestingParty"
              hangText="Requesting Party"><vspace/>A Subject that uses a
              Client to seek access to a protected resource. This Subject may
              be an Individual or an NPE. The Requesting Party and the
              Authorizing Party may be the same Subject or different
              Subjects.</t>

              <t anchor="RequestingPartyAgent"
              hangText="Requesting Party Agent"><vspace/>A Subject using a
              Client to seek access to a protected resource on behalf of a
              Requesting Party. Typically this Subject is an Individual acting
              on behalf of an NPE.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>Comments: The <xref target="UETA"/> defines two terms that are
          particularly relevant to understanding the interactions among UMA
          participants:<list style="symbols">
              <t>"'Automated transaction' means a transaction conducted or
              performed, in whole or in part, by electronic means or
              electronic records, in which the acts or records of one or both
              parties are not reviewed by an individual in the ordinary course
              in forming a contract, performing under an existing contract, or
              fulfilling an obligation required by the transaction."</t>

              <t>"'Electronic agent' means a computer program or an electronic
              or other automated means used independently to initiate an
              action or respond to electronic records or performances in whole
              or in part, without review or action by an individual."</t>
            </list>Where a Client is used by a human Requesting Party or a
          human Requesting Party Agent, at times human-computer interaction
          (HCI) will be required, but otherwise the access-attempt transaction
          is likely to be fully automatic from the perspective of the
          "requesting side". Furthermore, where the Authorizing Party and the
          Requesting Party are the same natural person, or where the
          Authorizing Party has set a policy that requires real-time approval
          through some out-of-band method, this person can expect to engage in
          HCI. Otherwise the access-attempt transaction is likely to be fully
          automatic from the perspective of the "authorizing side" because the
          access attempt is made without any requirement for the Authorizing
          Party to be present at run time.</t>

          <t>The National Strategy for Trusted Identities in Cyberspace <xref
          target="NSTIC"/> defines some terms similar to those defined
          here:<list style="symbols">
              <t>"An individual is a person engaged in an online transaction.
              Individuals are the first priority of the Strategy."</t>

              <t>"A non-person entity (NPE) may also require authentication in
              the Identity Ecosystem. NPEs can be organizations, hardware,
              networks, software, or services and are treated much like
              individuals within the Identity Ecosystem. NPEs may engage in or
              support a transaction."</t>

              <t>"The subject of a transaction may be an individual or an
              NPE."</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>UMA shares with NSTIC a priority to enable and empower individual
          people in the context of their online interactions. Note that this
          framework uses the terms Individual, NPE, and Subject exclusively
          for parties that have the capacity to take on contractual
          obligations, distinguishing them "from hardware, networks, software,
          or services", which do not have this capacity.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Abbreviations">
          <t>This framework uses the following abbreviations.<list
              style="hanging">
              <t anchor="UMA" hangText="UMA">User-Managed Access, the
              interoperability protocol defined by in <xref target="UMAcore"/>
              and the other specifications it includes normatively by
              reference.</t>

              <t anchor="API" hangText="API">Application programming
              interface.</t>

              <t anchor="PAT" hangText="PAT">Protection API token, as defined
              iin <xref target="UMAcore"/>.</t>

              <t anchor="AAT" hangText="AAT">Authorization API token, as
              defined in <xref target="UMAcore"/>.</t>

              <t anchor="RPT" hangText="RPT">Requesting party token, as
              defined in <xref target="UMAcore"/>.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>Comments: Tokens are critical to managing authorization and
          auditing of resource access. Section 1.3 is recommended reading for
          understanding what the various tokens represent and how they are
          issued and used. The RPT, in particular, has a definition that can
          vary depending on the RPT profile in use; thus, any obligations in
          this framework that depend on an RPT profile specify it by name.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Obligations of the Requesting Party">
        <section title="Requesting Party-Authorizing Party: Adhere-to-Terms">
          <t>When the Client successfully gains access from a Resource Server
          to a protected resource by wielding a valid "bearer" RPT associated
          with at least one currently valid permission for the type of access
          sought, the Requesting Party using that Client gains an obligation
          to the Authorizing Party to adhere to any terms it agreed to in
          order to gain the permission.</t>

          <t>Comments: This key obligation enables the end-to-end access
          authorization agreement that UMA exists to forge. At a previous
          stage, the Requesting Party asked for a relevant permission from the
          Authorization Server and might have had to provide claims of a
          promissory nature. Accepting access to the protected resource binds
          the Requesting Party to any terms it agreed to using the claims
          mechanism, for example, agreeing only to read the resource rather
          than modifying it, or forbearing from selling the resource data to
          someone else.</t>

          <t>Issues: Note that the obligation goes into effect the first time
          a Client gains access under the power of a "currently valid
          permission". If there was more than one valid permission attached to
          different sets of promises, if a secure record was not kept by the
          Resource Server and/or Authorization Server of which permission was
          used for granting access, ambiguity is introduced. Defining and
          using RPT profiles other than the "bearer" profile might lessen the
          potential ambiguity.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Requesting Party-Authorizing Party: Make-Factual-Representations">
          <t>When the Requesting Party provides, or facilitates the sourcing
          of, claims to an Authorization Server in a claims-gathering flow,
          the Requesting Party gains an obligation to the Authorizing Party to
          stand behind any factual representations it makes in order to gain
          the permission, to the best of its knowledge at the time it makes
          them.</t>

          <t>Comments: This obligation is gained during the providing of
          actual claims, rather than at the time of AAT issuance or protected
          resource access, because factual claims might age and expire. Where
          the Requesting Party supplies or sources claims in a manner that can
          be verified by the Authorization Server, the risk imposed by this
          need for "trust" can be reduced. Note that UMA defines an optional
          OpenID Connect claim profile that provides one way to collect
          trusted claims from third-party claim providers.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Requesting Party-Authorization Server Operator: Supply-Truthful-Claims">
          <t>When the Authorization Server issues an AAT to a Client and for
          as long as the AAT is valid, the Requesting Party using that Client
          gains an obligation to the Authorization Server Operator to supply
          or facilitate access to truthful claims required for access
          authorization at this AM, when it chooses to supply them, to the
          best of its knowledge at the time it supplies them.</t>

          <t>Comments: At a later stage, the Requesting Party might be asked
          to provide claims to support authorization processes at this
          Authorization Server for accessing <spanx>all</spanx> resources
          protected by this Authorization Server, managed by any Authorizing
          Parties, at any Resource Servers. The Requesting Party's
          responsibility to act in good faith in interacting with this
          Authorization Server begins now because factual claims it supplies
          could be reused for more than one access-sharing relationship. This
          obligation can be removed through AAT revocation.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Requesting Party-Resource Server Operator: Is-Legitimate-Bearer">
          <t>When the Authorization Server issues an RPT to a Client and for
          as long as the RPT is valid, the Requesting Party using that Client
          gains an obligation to the Resource Server Operator to represent the
          legitimate bearer of the RPT or its authorized representative, and
          not to allow others to impersonate the Requesting Party.</t>

          <t>Comments: In the case where the "bearer" RPT profile or any other
          bearer-style RPT profile is used, the token may not be bound in any
          technically confirmable way to the specific client and requesting
          party it applies to. Defining and using different UMA token profiles
          can mitigate the risk of failure or malice on the Requesting Party's
          part. The "authorized representative" phrase is intended to clear
          the way for token-chaining profiles or similar.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Obligations of the Resource Server Operator">
        <section title="Resource Server Operator-Authorizing Party: Delegate-Protection">
          <t>When the Authorization Server issues a PAT to a Resource Server
          and as long as the PAT is valid, the Resource Server Operator gains
          an obligation to the Authorizing Party to delegate protection
          services to the Authorization Server Operator for the set of
          protectable resources for which it represents this capability to the
          Authorizing Party, and to respect the authorization data that the
          Authorization Server has associated with an RPT when the Resource
          Server subsequently allows or disallows access by the Client that
          presented that RPT.</t>

          <t>Comments: Once the Authorization Server Operator becomes the
          Authorizing Party's authorization proxy, it begins relying on the
          Resource Server Operator in other, more specific ways. The Resource
          Server has the opportunity to inspect AM-issued permissions or take
          other actions that delegate protection responsibility to the
          Authorization Server at a later stage, but its responsibility for
          respecting them begins now. The specific protection services made
          available to the Resource Server by the Authorization Server differ
          depending on the RPT profile in use. This obligation can be removed
          through PAT revocation.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Resource Server Operator-Authorization Server Operator: Register-Accurately-and-Timely">
          <t>When the Authorization Server issues a PAT to the Resource Server
          and as long as the PAT is valid, the Resource Server Operator gains
          an obligation to the Authorization Server Operator to register
          resource set descriptions accurately and timely according to the
          Authorizing Party&rsquo;s expressed instructions for protection.</t>

          <t>Comments: At a later stage, the Resource Server has the
          opportunity to register resource sets, but its responsibility for
          performing this task begins now. The Resource Server Operator may
          have contracted with the Authorizing Party for service-level
          agreements to respond specifically to timeliness needs and so on.
          This obligation can be removed through PAT revocation.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Resource Server Operator-Authorization Server Operator: Respect-Permissions">
          <t>When the Resource Server successfully introspects a "bearer" RPT,
          the Resource Server Operator gains an obligation to the
          Authorization Server Operator to respect the permissions that the
          Authorization Server has associated with the RPT when the Resource
          Server subsequently allows or disallows access by the Client that
          presented that RPT.</t>

          <t>Comments: The Resource Server Operator, as a Subject that is
          otherwise potentially not obligated to the Authorization Server
          Operator, carries a great deal of responsibility here not to allow
          access where the Authorization Server has not granted permission and
          to make every effort to grant access where the Authorization Server
          has granted permission. Its interpretation of scopes and permissions
          is not directly auditable by the Authorization Server. Further,
          issues can arise from the skew between permission validity periods
          and actual access. Defining and using different RPT profiles can
          mitigate the risk of failure or malice on the Resource Server
          Operator's part.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Resource Server Operator-Requesting Party: Give-Accurate-Access">
          <t>When the Resource Server responds in any fashion to a Client's
          access request, the Resource Server Operator gains an obligation to
          the Requesting Party to give accurate access to the protected
          resource according to whether the Requesting Party has permission to
          do so.</t>

          <t>Comments: The Resource Server Operator, as a Subject that is
          otherwise potentially not obligated to the Authorization Server
          Operator, carries a great deal of responsibility here to make every
          effort to grant access where the Authorization Server has associated
          authorization data to guide access. Its interpretation of scopes and
          permissions, particularly in the case where the RPT presented by the
          Client uses the "bearer" RPT profile, is not entirely auditable by
          the requester or Authorization Server. Further, issues can arise
          from the skew between permission validity periods and actual access.
          Defining and using different RPT profiles can mitigate the risk of
          failure on the Resource Server Operator's part.</t>

          <t>Issues: The relying party traditionally always has the right of
          refusal. The resource server may have additional authorization
          context available only to it that suggests it should not grant
          access, for example. Should this obligation be struck?</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Obligations of the Authorization Server Operator">
        <section title="Authorization Server Operator-Authorizing Party: Follow-Policies-Accurately-and-Timely">
          <t>When the Authorization Server issues a PAT to the Resource Server
          and as long as the PAT is valid, the Authorization Server Operator
          gains an obligation to the Authorizing Party to adhere to the
          Authorizing Party's policies accurately and timely in granting
          permissions.</t>

          <t>Comments: At a later stage, the Authorization Server will require
          the Resource Server to present the PAT whenever it uses the
          Authorization Server&rsquo;s protection API on behalf of this
          Authorizing Party. The Authorization Server Operator may have
          contracted with the Authorizing Party for service-level agreements
          to respond specifically to timeliness needs and so on. This
          obligation can be removed through PAT revocation.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Authorization Server Operator-Resource Server Operator: Follow-Policies-Accurately-and-Timely">
          <t>When the Resource Server registers a requested permission at the
          Authorization Server, the Authorization Server Operator gains an
          obligation to the Resource Server Operator to adhere to the
          Authorizing Party&rsquo;s authorization policies accurately and
          timely in associating authorization data with RPTs presented with
          the registered permission's ticket.</t>

          <t>Comments: At a later stage, when a Client approaches the
          Authorization Server presenting an RPT and a permission ticket, the
          Authorization Server matches Authorizing Party policies to the
          requested permission to drive any requests for claims and ultimate
          authorization processes, but its responsibility for performing this
          task begins now.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Authorization Server Operator-Requesting Party: Request-Limited-Claims">
          <t>When the Authorization Server issues an AAT to a Client and as
          long as the AAT is valid, the Authorization Server Operator gains an
          obligation to the Requesting Party to request only claims that
          support the purpose of satisfying an Authorizing Party's policy.</t>

          <t>Comments: At a later stage, the Authorization Server might ask
          the Requesting Party to provide claims for specific permission
          purposes at multiple Resource Servers and/or for multiple
          Authorizing Parties, but its responsibility begins now. This
          obligation can be removed through AAT revocation.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Obligations of the Authorizing Party">
        <section title="Authorizing Party-Requesting Party: Adhere-to-Terms">
          <t>When the Authorization Server responds positively to a Client's
          request for authorization, the Authorizing Party gains an obligation
          to the Requesting Party using that Client to adhere to the terms
          offered to and accepted by the Requesting Party in the form of
          requests for claims driven by the Authorizing Party's policy at the
          Authorization Server.</t>

          <t>Comments: For example, the Authorizing User cannot subsequently
          protest or sue the Requesting Party for resale of the user&rsquo;s
          data if this was allowed by the terms of access authorization.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Authorizing Party-Authorization Server Operator: Introduce-Resource-Server">
          <t>When the Authorization Server issues a PAT to a Resource Server
          and as long as the PAT is valid, the Authorizing Party gains an
          obligation to the Authorization Server Operator to introduce the
          desired Resource Server to this Authorization Server in outsourcing
          protection of this Resource Server's resources.</t>

          <t>Comments: How the Resource Server learned of the Authorization
          Server's location is out of band for UMA; it is the Authorizing
          Party's responsibility to check that it has been redirected to an
          acceptable Authorization Server before the Authorization Server
          successfully issues the PAT. This obligation can be removed through
          PAT revocation.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Authorizing Party-Resource Server Operator: Introduce-Authorization-Server">
          <t>When the Authorization Server issues a PAT to a Resource Server
          and as long as the PAT is valid, the Authorizing Party gains an
          obligation to the Resource Server Operator to introduce the desired
          Authorization Server to this Resource Server in outsourcing
          protection of this Resource Server's resources.</t>

          <t>Comments: Once the Authorization Server Operator becomes the
          Authorizing Party&rsquo;s authorization proxy, the Resource Server
          Operator begins relying on it in other, more specific ways. How the
          Authorizing Party indicated the desired Authorization Server to the
          host is out of band for UMA; it is the Authorizing Party's
          responsibility to check that it has been redirected to an acceptable
          Authorization Server before the Authorization Server successfully
          issues the PAT. This obligation can be removed through PAT
          revocation.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>The current editor of this document is Eve Maler of XMLgrrl.com. The
      following people are co-authors:<list style="symbols">
          <t>Domenico Catalano, Oracle Corp.</t>

          <t>Kevin Cox, Edentiti</t>

          <t>Sal D'Agostino, IDmachines</t>

          <t>Susan Morrow, Avoco Secure</t>

          <t>Dazza Greenwood, Civics.com</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Additional contributors to this document include the Kantara UMA Work
      Group participants, a list of whom can be found at <xref
      target="UMAnitarians"/>. The co-authors and contributors thank Scott
      David, Dazza Greenwood, and Tom Smedinghoff for offering their legal
      expertise and insight in the preparation of this document.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml' ?>

      <reference anchor="UMAcore"
                 target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-hardjono-oauth-umacore">
        <front>
          <title>User-Managed Access (UMA) Profile of OAuth 2.0</title>

          <author initials="T." surname="Hardjono">
            <organization>MIT</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="27" month="December" year="2012"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="UMAnitarians"
                 target="http://kantarainitiative.org/confluence/display/uma/Participant+Roster">
        <front>
          <title>UMA Participant Roster</title>

          <author initials="E." surname="Maler">
            <organization>Maler</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2012"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="UETA"
                 target="http://www.law.upenn.edu/bll/archives/ulc/fnact99/1990s/ueta99.htm">
        <front>
          <title>Uniform Electronic Transactions Act</title>

          <author initials="T." surname="Smedinghoff">
            <organization>National Conference of Commissioners on Uniform
            State Laws</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="1999"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="NSTIC"
                 target="http://www.whitehouse.gov/sites/default/files/rss_viewer/NSTICstrategy_041511.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>National Strategy for Trusted Identities in
          Cyberspace</title>

          <author initials="" surname="">
            <organization>US Federal Government</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="15" month="April" year="2011"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="UMAFAQ-swim"
                 target="http://kantarainitiative.org/confluence/display/uma/UMA+FAQ#UMAFAQ-WhatistheUMAprotocolflow">
        <front>
          <title>UMA Frequently Asked Questions: What is the UMA protocol
          flow?</title>

          <author initials="" surname="">
            <organization>US Federal Government</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="" month="January" year="2013"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section anchor="History" title="Document History">
      <t>NOTE: To be removed by RFC editor before publication as an RFC.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
